Guide to the Herman Axelbank Motion Picture Film Collection 1896-1977
Hoover Institution Archives
- German officers in the Baltic Region (312-314) White soldiers execute Bolshevik POWs--prisoners lie on the ground while their shoes are removed; three at a time stand with backs to an open grave; one prisoner continues to smile up to the time of his execution; firing squad executes them; they fall into grave (314-373), 1919; Segment 4; 05:52:27 (Reel 25)
  312 (5/578)
  Civil War, 1918-1921--German intervention; Executions and executioners; Civil War, 1918-1921--Campaigns--Northwestern front; Prisoners of war; Civil War, 1918-1921--Prisons and prisoners
  Baltic Region
  Sound: 314-373
- Map showing Civil War situation (0-12) queue of women with tea pots and sacks in Moscow (12-20) Trotsky with soldiers (20-26) Red Army soldiers between Kazan and the Urals; firing field artillery; picture of Marx above a tent entrance; Red Army soldier with bandage around his head playing a board game with another soldier; battlefield scenes; funeral procession in Yaroslavl' for Bolshevik soldiers killed by Whites (26-59) Zinov'ev and Pozern leave for the front (59-79) Lenin on balcony addressing troops leaving for the Denikin Front (79-111) cavalry; troops riding on top of a train (111-118) Red Army in combat on the Denikin Front; Budenny's cavalry; sunflowers; field with haystacks on fire (same sequence as on reel 25, segment 1) (118-136) ruins of a Siberian village following a punitive raid by Kolchak's troops; American officer with Czechoslovak and other Allied military figures inspecting corpses of victims (136-146), 1919; Segment 1; 05:59: 06:03:56 (Reel 26)
  0 (6/009)
  Trotskii, Lev; Zinov'ev, Grigorii; Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich; Pozern, Boris Pavlovich
  Civil War, 1918-1921--Campaigns--Siberia; Civil War, 1918-1921--Campaigns--Urals; Soldiers; Funeral service--Red Army soldiers; Civil War, 1918-1921--Campaigns--Southern front; Military ceremonies--Soviet period
  Moscow; Yaroslavl'; Siberia
  A; B. Battlefield scenes. D. Map
  Sound: 0-59; 129-134; 136-146
- Defense-of Petrograd from IUdenich--Trotsky exhorts; civilians with rifles march by; military equipment in the streets; soldiers at train station; sentry checks documents of the occupants of a car marked with a red cross; charge of Kronstadt sailors; Kronstadt sailors eating soup in courtyard of Gachina Palace (146-182) photo of Lenin and Trotsky reviewing troops on Red Square, Nov. 7(182-194) Lenin in a crowd during military review (194-209) Trotsky and Pozern (209-218) Trotsky and Lenin reviewing troops; Lenin in crowd; soldiers on parade (194-263) infantry charge; exploding shells; cavalry charge (263-271) parade in celebration of Kolchak's defeat; school children marching; poster: Down with intervention (271-291) artillery captured from Whites displayed on Red Square (291-294), 1919; Segment 2; 06:03:56 06:08:07 (Reel 26)
  146 (6/086)
  Trotskii, Lev; Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich; Pozern, Boris Pavlovich
  Civil War, 1918-1921--Campaigns--Northwestern front; Kronstadt sailors; October Revolution (November 1917 N.S.)--Anniversary, 1919; Military ceremonies--Soviet period; Civil War, 1918-1921--Campaigns--Siberia; Processions--Soviet period
  Leningrad; Gachina; Moscow
  A; B. Battlefield scenes
  Sound: 146-156; 164-173; 176-183; 271-294
- Lenin in his Kremlin office, Feb. 20 (294-325) Trotsky addresses 9th Party Congress, April 17(325-333) Kalinin (333-340) Trotsky followed by Muralov and delegates to 2d Congress of the Comintern, marching, May 1;Trotsky salutes (340-346) Trotsky presents banners to most heroic regiments of Red Army (346-351) military parade (351-354) Lenin at cornerstone laying of monument to Karl Marx, May 1(354-406), 1920; Segment 3; 06:08:07 06:11 (Reel 26)
  294 (6/152)
  Trotskii, Lev; Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich; Kalinin, Mikhail Ivanovich; Muralov, Aleksandr Ivanovich
  Communist International. 2d Congress, Moscow and Leningrad, 1920; May Day (Labor holiday), 1920; Military ceremonies--Soviet period; Kommunisticheskaia partiia Sovetskogo Soiuza. 9. sezd, Moscow, 1920; Cornerstones, Laying of
  Sound: 294-325; 333-340; 347-351
- Lenin speaking at another cornerstone laying, May 1;behind him, banner with inscription: Today we are laying the cornerstone of a monument to emancipated labor (0-10) demobilized Red Army soldiers digging with shovels, plowing (10-23) Krupskaia addressing Red Army encampment (23-28) Krupskaia on boat with binoculars (28-33) checkpoint at the Finnish border (33-49) photo of Lenin speaking from platform, Moscow, May 5;Trotsky standing at right of platform (49-55) Trotsky arriving in Kiev, June 20(55-65), 1920; Segment 1; 06:11:22 (Reel 27)
  0 (6/199)
  Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich; Krupskaia, Nadezhda Konstantinovna; Trotskii, Lev
  May Day (Labor holiday), 1920; Civil War, 1918-1921; Cornerstones, Laying of
  Moscow; Kiev
  Sound: 10-23
- Second Congress of the Comintern (met July 19 in Petrograd, July 23-August 7 in Moscow)--parades; foreign delegates greeted on arrival in Petrograd; delegates taken to Uritsky Palace (formerly Tauride Palace) where first sessions are held (65-117) Zinov'ev, President of the Comintern, enters the Palace; Zorin and Zinov'ev talk on the platform; Zinov'ev delivers the opening address; speeches by Kalinin; Levi (delegate from Germany); Balabanoff, Secretary of the Comintern; Rosmer (France); Serrati (Italy); Marchlewski (Poland); Gruber (Austria); Radek; Lenin, Radek, Balabanoff on platform; Lenin speaks; delegates applaud, rise to their feet (117-200), July 19, 1920; Segment 2; 06:16:59 (Reel 27)
  65 (6/223)
  Rosmer, Alfred; Steinhardt, Karl; Radek, Karl; Zinov'ev, Grigorii; Levi, Paul; Serrati, Giacinto Menotti; Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich; Zorin, S. S.; Marchlewski, Julian; Kalinin, Mikhail Ivanovich; Balabanoff, Angelica
  Communist International. 2d Congress, Moscow and Leningrad, 1920; Processions--Soviet period
- Second Congress of the Comintern (cont.)--outside the palace, workers of Petrograd present Comintern delegates with seven banners (200-218) delegates, including Bukharin, Zinov'ev, Radek, John Reed, Louise Bryant, leaving hall after first session (218-227) parade, delegates participating (227-243) ceremony in honor of martyrs of the Revolution on Mars Field--John Reed at head of procession, then on left; wreath placed on grave of martyrs; Zinov'ev in the crowd, Reed on left; Lenin in the crowd, Zorin on left (243-283) Petrograd garrison parades in honor of delegates (283-301) mass meeting on Uritsky Square (Winter Palace Square); Balabanoff, Serrati, Zinov'ev on speakers' stand; Bombacci of Italy speaking (301-363), July 19, 1920; Segment 3; 06:17:00 06:21:33 (Reel 27)
  200 (6/269)
  Bukharin, Nikolai Ivanovich; Zinov'ev, Grigorii; Radek, Karl; Reed, John; Bryant, Louise; Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich; Zorin, S. S.; Balabanoff, Angelica; Serrati, Giancinto Menotti; Bombacci, Nicola Communist International. 2d Congress, Moscow and Leningrad, 1920; Military ceremonies--Soviet period; Memorial service--Martyrs of February Revolution
  Sound: 243-253
- Second Congress of the Comintern (cont.)--crowds on Uritsky Square; Lenin addresses the crowd; Zinov'ev; Serrati; Balabanoff; Zinov'ev addresses the crowd; crowd begins to disperse (0-42) ships on the Neva River decorated in honor of the Comintern Congress; tableaux presented on the steps of former stock exchange building: Communism vs. capitalism; fireworks in honor of the Congress (42-52) Moscow; Kremlin; delegates during session of Congress; Lenin on platform, next to Serrati; Lenin addresses delegates (52-76) Lenin and Krupskaia leaving the hall (76-84), July 19-Aug. 7, 1920; Segment 1; 06:21:34: (Reel 28)
  0 (6/322)
  Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich; Serrati, Giacinto Menotti; Balabanoff, Angelica; Zinov'ev, Grigorii; Krupskaia, Nadezhda Konstantinovna Communist International. 2d Congress, Moscow and Leningrad, 1920 Leningrad; Moscow
  A; D. Map
- American miners leaving by ship for Russia; boys wrestle on deck; women sew banner (84-122) Kuznetsk Basin, mining and metallurgical region--Bill Haywood, American IWW leader who jumped bail and fled to Russia, stands amidst miners (Haywood is the other American besides John Reed buried at the Kremlin wall) (122-166) Haywood seated at a desk in Moscow (166-174) Turkestan woman delegate, speaking on Red Square, thanks Soviet leaders for granting independence and self-determination to Turkestan (174-177) Agit-prop train (propaganda murals on sides) (177-180) Lenin at window of his Kremlin apartment; Lenin, holding cat, with Krupskaia (180-215) photo of Lenin in his Kremlin office (215-221) Trotsky in his Kremlin office (221-223), 1920; Segment 2; 06:23:57 06:27:50 (Reel 28)
  84 (6/347)
  Haywood, William Dudley; Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich; Trotskii, Lev; Krupskaia, Nadezhda Konstantinovna
  Immigrants, American, to the Soviet Union; Miners, American; Industrial Workers of the World; Agit-prop trains; Minorities; Coal-miners
  United States; Kuznetsk Basin; Turkestan
  Sound: 222-223
- Ludwig Martens, Soviet Ambassador to the United States (who was recalled when the U.S. declined to recognize the Soviet government) being seen off at NY pier by American Communists (film shot by Herman Axelbank) (223-233) Rykov delivers eulogy at John Reed's grave at the Kremlin Wall; the grave with headstone (233-244) drawing of Wrangel; Red infantry, cavalry attacks; map of Soviet Republic after White armies driven out (244-266) Frunze reviews troops (266-269) Voroshilov and Budenny on horseback with troops at victory celebration (269-273) victory parade at Odessa (273-278) victory parade of Red Army at Astrakhan (278-281) victory parade at Kiev (281-285) scenes of destroyed town, vehicles (285-297) Daghestan-funeral of nationalists (opposers of Daghestan's incorporation into the Soviet Union) (297-317) Stalin and Ordzhenikidze (317-325) Zinov'ev addresses outdoor meeting in Kronstadt (325-351), 1920, 1921; Segment 3 (Reel 28)
  223 (6/387)
  Martens, Ludwig Christian Alexander Karl; Rykov, Aleksei Ivanovich; Reed, John; Vrangel', Petr Nikolaevich; Budennyi, Semen Mikhailovich; Stalin Iosif; Frunze, Mikhail Vasil'evich; Voroshilov, Kliment Efremovich; Ordzhenikidze, Grigorii Konstantinovich; Axelbank, Herman
  Funeral service--Reed, John; Military ceremonies--Soviet period; Civil War, 1918-1921--Campaigns--Southern front; Civil War, 1918-1921; Processions--Soviet period; Funeral service--Daghestan nationalists; Foreign relations--United States; Communists--United States
  New York; United States; Moscow; Crimea; Odessa; Astrakhan; Kiev; Daghestan; Kronstadt
  Sound: 262-266; 297-325
- Reel # 8 (See Reel 8 description above) (Videotape 7)
- Reel #40, 7:15:16:29-07:25:44
  - Religion lampooned, 1923
  - British political figure lampooned.
  - "Tomorrow Germany!" on white banner of truck.
  - Floats, revolutionary slogans.
  - November 7, 1923,Moscow celebration -- Sklianskii, secretary to Trotsky (murdered by the OGPU in the U.S.), Kamenev, Kalinin, on rostrum -- Red Garrison parades -- Frunze, General Yegorov, General Kamenev, General Muralov, Kamenev. Trotsky in Moscow.
  - January 21, 1924,Lenin dies at Gorki -- Lenin's funeral (unmarred by later "Stalinized" censored versions that de-deleted all his victims) -- January 23,coffin borne to railroad station at Gorki, for trip to Moscow -- Rykov, Bukharin, and Molotov carrying Lenin's casket to railroad station -- Lashevitz, Unschlicht, Ordjonikidze -- coffin placed in railroad car -- from railroad, coffin carried to Hall of Trade Unions in Moscow -- inside Hall of Trade Unions, at coffin: Zinoviev and Stalin -- _______________ and Stalin -- Lenin in open casket -- Krupskaia -- Maria Ul'ianova, Lenin's sister, near Krupskaia -- Maria, Krupskaia, Kalinin, Tomsky -- Zetkin wipes tear -- Krupskaia -- Uglianov and Zinoviev -- diplomats and foreign dignitaries pay respects -- Bukharin, Zinoviev and Krupskaia -- January 27,casket borne to Red Square wood mausoleum -- Zinoviev, Kamenev an Stalin carry coffin -- cortege, Moscow street corner -- snow -- Voroshilov and Bukharin carry casket -- Molotov -- "Lenin Our Immortality" inscription -- mausoleum, atop -- masses of mourners, frozen breaths, 30 below zero -- Rykov, Kamenev, and Bukharin -- Yevdokimov speaks from script -- soldiers, flag -- Krupskaia -- frozen breath of masses -- Yevdokimov with paper in hand -- Rykov, profile -- marchers past mausoleum -- coffin "dissolves" into Lenin -- mausoleum chamber., 1924
  - May 1, 1924, May Day celebration -- Yaroslavsky, Kalinin, on rostrum
- Reel #118, Note: Video noise on time-coded tapes; 16mm film is free of this.; 08:00 (Videotape 8)
  The following six films of the Herman Axelbank Collection were duplicated through funding from The L.J. Skaggs and Mary C. Skaggs Foundation. They comprise a special grouping on the topic of "Jews in the Soviet Union" and "Jews under Nazism." This is a direct transcription from Herman Axelbank's notes giving brief descriptions of the contents of each reel.
  - "Jews under Communism" (rare films of Jewish people in Russia, 1917-1973) -- films of Jewish people in Russia, under Stalin-Khrushchev-Brezhnev decimation of all Jewish cultural life, including murder victims: poet Peretz Markish, speaking Yiddish; director Mikhoels speaking in Russian; Eisenstein; physicist Kapitza; author David Bergelson and entire personnel of "Jewish Anti-Fascist Committee" -- artists, writers and cultural leaders murdered by Stalin on August 12, 1952-- including the Jewish doctors in Stalin's notorious "doctors' frame-up" saved by latter's death in 1953 -- including most recent persecution of Jewish would-be emigrants and secret Jewish cultural gathering in the woods., 1952
  - Jewish Workers' Party in Petrograd parade -- procession to Mars Field in funeral of martyrs of revolution., 1917
  - Banner inscribed in Jewish.
  - Kalinin takes tea with old Jew in village square, symbolic of comparison with Tsar's anti-semitism., 1918
  - Jewish family depicted in silent film "Kombrig Ivanov.", 1923
  - Jewish colony in Crimea (Soviet government's several attempts at special Jewish communes)., 1925
  - "Finken" is the name of this colony, meaning "sparks" -- Lenin government encouraged "autonomous" Jewish settlements in Crimea, in line with "emancipation of national minorities and flowering of their cultures under Communism" -- later liquidated by Stalin, like Chechens, Tannu-Tuvans and Kalmyks.
  - Caucasian Jewish colony -- Jewish open-air school -- Communist commissar points out to cameraman modern Communist curriculum in contrast with old religious rabbi seen teaching his Bible class -- this outdoor Hebrew religious class is probably the last of its kind filmed in Russia prior to Stalin's obliteration of all Jewish culture., 1927
  - Jewish collective farm in Bokhara celebrates fifth anniversary of its founding -- Moscow commissar greets them -- traditional Jewish dances (Stalin soon liquidated this collective)., 1928
  - Crimean Jewish colony -- Jewish settlers drilling for water -- relying on Soviet pledges, they toiled unceasingly to build up this settlement, only to be driven from it later by Stalin -- members scattered to other regions, with most of the pioneers liquidated or shipped to Siberian slave-camps where they died of exposure and starvation, according to one escapee, a Jewish writer now in the U.S.
- Reel #119, 08:06:00 VHS
  - Jewish colony in Russia -- sign reads "Chahklahyer Schula for Peasant Youth" (Yiddish script) -- where Jewish cultural activities were permitted for a while, in Yiddish (Hebrew, language of the Bible, was forbidden) -- Jewish schoolchildren seen in various activities -- classes, exercises, etc.-- Communist theory propagated by "Yevsek" commissars (Jewish section of Communist party which functioned for a time prior to Stalin's anti-Jewish purges)., 1929
  - "Gift from Moscow" -- a radio for "education of workers of this collective."
  - Young "pioneer" indoctrinates his old-fashioned grandfather. Class in Marxism.
  - Jewish state theatre in Moscow., 1934
  - Performing Shakespeare's "King Lear" in Yiddish.
  - Solomon Mikhoels as "King Lear" and Ziskind as the jester -- Director Mikhoels was murdered by Stalin in Minsk in 1948 -- Ziskind was murdered by Stalin together with many other Jewish intellectuals in August, 1952.
  - Jewish anti-Fascist committee, Moscow, in session (soundtrack) --Sergei Eisenstein, film director (second from left) -- Peter Kapitze, physicist -- David Ziskind, leading actor, Jewish state theatre -- Zak, famous pianist (on right)., 1941
  - Mikhoels speaks in Russian (soundtrack).
  - Peter Markish (Jewish poet) speaks in Yiddish.
- Reel #120, 08:15:31
  - Hitler's Germany.
  - Book burning -- anti-Jewish slogans smeared on store windows- hooliganism -- handful of Jews flee Germany -- most are trapped in German hell -- Jewish youth, Greenspan, kills Hitler ambassador Vom Rath, is tortured to death in German captivity -- massacre of Jews in Germany begins -- synagogues set on fire with worshippers locked inside -- Jewish shops smeared with "Jude."
  - Destruction of Warsaw -- terror., 1939
  - Hitler inspects his slaughter in Poland.
  - Jewish hostages in Warsaw (German cameramen).
  - Anti-Jewish placards.
  - Warsaw ghetto (German cameramen)., 1941
- Reel #121, 08:24
  - Entire Jewish population of Warsaw herded into small area, sealed off by a brick wall, where they perish from malnutrition and disease., 1941
  - Monstrosities filmed by German cameramen.
  - Mass starvation of entire population.
  - Children who scaled the wall and tried to re-enter with scraps of food, are searched by Germans and made to give up scraps, then murdered.
  - Daily burials.
  - Warsaw ghetto uprising., 1943
  - Ghetto fighters with handful of smuggled small arms, hold off might of German armor for almost three months, starting April, 1943, until entire area is devastated by German artillery, and remnants of fighters murdered.
  - Victims driven to death camps.
  - Murder camps.
- Reel #122, 08:34
  - Gas chambers., 1943
  - Mass murder of millions of men, women and children.
  - Eichmann -- Hitler -- Himmler.
  - "Elite" German battalions.
  - "SS" killers.
  - Hitler and Himmler, reviewing "elite" killer-brigades in Berlin.
  - Destruction of Warsaw ghetto., 08:38
  - Execution of remnants of ghetto fighters.
- Reel #123, 08:40:34
  - Jewish soldiers and officers in Red Army receive decorations in Kremlin -- they are among bravest of fighters against the Germans, proportionally getting highest battle citations., 1943
  - "Jewish doctors' plot" -- doctors framed by Stalin henchmen into false confessions -- Stalin's death saved them.
  - Jewish communities uprooted from towns and villages where they had lived for a thousand years, and forcibly removed to far regions., 08:46:18
- Reel #90 (Videotape 9)
  The following four reels of the Herman Axelbank collection were duplicated through funding from the American Broadcasting Companies, Inc. This is a direct transcription from Herman Axelbank's notes giving brief descriptions of the contents of each reel.
  - Lublin captured -- horror of German murder camp Maidanek -- German murder barracks where Germans slaughtered 1,500,000 men, women, and children and shipped their clothes, hair, and gold fillings to Berlin -- deathtraps, ovens, hair, teeth, watches, rings., 1944 (23 July)
- Reel #93
  - Inhabitants return, carts -- road sign: "Gleiwitz" pointer -- white flags in windows -- Auschwitz murder barracks -- pitiful remnant of camp inmates saved by Germans' flight -- railroad yard abandoned by Germans -- torture victims - frozen naked bodies in freight cars - Germans had no time to cover traces -- naked corpses of mother and baby in freight car - clothing of victims strewn about in snow at railroad siding -- -- frozen corpses on snowy ground alongside freight cars -- frozen baby in freight car -- tattooed arms of victims miraculously saved by Russian advance -- German woman in Gleiwitz, well fed and warmly clothed -- road sign: "Berlin 200 km" -- Russians drive on to Berlin., 1945
  - German sneak attack -- Russian airfields destroyed -- murder and plunder -- Russian resistance -- Brest fortress defended almost a month against a German division., 1941 (22 June)
- Reel #97
  - Endless lines of German prisoners -- 57,000 Germans marched through streets of Moscow (summer 1944)-- Minsk recaptured -- Brest -- Byalistok -- Germans destroy, burn all prior retreat -- dynamiting by Germans in retreat -- Lublin captured -- Marshal Grechko -- Marshal Malinovsky -- Odessa and Kishenev liberated -- prisoners, hands raised -- Petsamo, in the north, captured -- Red Army enters Norway -- Kirkenes taken, Russians liberate hundreds of Norwegian freedom fighters -- Vistula defenses smashed -- battlements of German "Vistula Line.", 1944
  - Warsaw captured, 17 January-- road sign: "Berlin 120" -- "Berlin 80" -- Germany entered by Red Army -- Distance covered, from Moscow -- tortuous, slow advance westward, in retrospect -- Zhukov in dugout at front -- Berlin - main blow by troops of 1st Byelorussian front -- air offensive -- battle for Berlin -- Russian big guns, German defenses -- tank battle -- Berlin entered by Russian advance patrols -- under siege inside Berlin prior to capitulation -- queues for food -- General Vaigling interrogated by Russians -- fighting inside Berlin -- Uniformed Russian woman handling out bread loaves to Germans -- Red soldier aiding old German -- Hitler's chancery, where he committed suicide, captured -- Goebbels's charred remains -- 2 May:Reichstag attacked and captured -- Berlin capitulates -- Russian inscriptions on columns -- concentration-camp inmates freed, cheer liberators -- Warsaw, Bucharest, Sofia, Budapest Belgrade, and Prague - cheering crowds hail Russian troops., 1945
- Reel #99
  - Feb.: Yalta conference, three-power conference at Yalta -- Churchill, Stalin, Roosevelt -- 27 Apr.: Russians meet with Americans on Elbe -- June: Beirut (Poland) with Stalin in Kremlin -- "Lublin Committee" rules Poland -- Potsdam conference: Stalin, Truman, Churchill; Molotov, Vishinsky, Byrnes, Bohlen -- 8 Aug.: Russo-Japanese war -- Russians attack Japanese in Manchuria, land, sea, and air battles, Japanese surrender -- 25 Aug.: Russians enter Korea -- northern Korea occupied by Red Army -- communists stage wild greeting of Red troops -- Chinese-Soviet friendship treaty, in Kremlin -- Stalin-Chiang Kai-shek pact, while former backs Mao for communist takeover., 1945
- Reel #29, 10:00:00 (Videotape 10)
  - Beseiged Kronstadt sailors demanding a more democratic rule and a constituent assembly are battered down by Red Army under Marshall Tukhachevsky -- Commander Dybenko (of Baltic Fleet) speaks -- victorious Bolsheviks leaving bat tered battleship "Sevastopol' " after massacre of mutineers -- Lenin and Trotsky among Red soldiers who put down Kronstadt Mutiny -- behind Lenin is Voroshilov -- at 10th Party Congress (under Stalin, this photo was "doctored", "Stalinized" -- photo above, as it now appears in Soviet history books (76) -- Lenin on April 25, 1921 -- May 1,May Day celebration on Uritskii Square, Petrograd -- Zinoviev, President of Petrograd Soviet, and aides review the parade -- Moscow, May Day celebration on Red Square -- Trotsky addresses graduates of military academy -- Trotsky reviews Red Army -- Red cavalry -- Lenin at 10th All-Russian Conference in Moscow., 1921
- Reel #30, 10:10:50-10:16:50